Charles Monteith collection, 1948-1994
Emory University
Charles Monteith collection, 1948-1994
Monteith, Charles.
Manuscript Collection No. 789
.5 linear ft. (2 boxes)
Collection of materials relating to Faber and Faber editor Charles Monteith including letters written between 1948 and 1994 from many of his literary associates.
Emory University Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library
Source
Purchase, 1996.
Restrictions on access
Special restrictions apply: Letters from Seamus Heaney are closed to researchers.
Biographical
Charles Monteith was a commissioning editor at the publishing house of Faber and Faber beginning in 1954. He later served as Chairman of the firm from 1977 to 1980. He continued to serve as a senior editorial consultant until his death in 1995.
Scope and Content Note
The Charles Monteith collection includes letters written between 1948 and 1994 from many of Monteith's literary associates from his years at Faber and Faber. Present are single letters or cards from W.H. Auden, Samuel Beckett, William Golding, Wilson Harris, John Holloway, Robert Lowell, Paul Muldoon, Norman Nicholson, Anne Ridler, Stephen Spender, and Angus Wilson. Multiple letters are present from Alan Bennett, Douglas Dunn, W.S. Graham, Seamus Heaney (restricted), Ted Hughes, John McGahern, Marianne Moore, Richard Murphy, and A.L. Rowse. These letters cover a wide range of subjects but often relate to writing and publishing. There is also a small amount of W.H. Auden manuscript material in the collection.
Arrangement Note
Arranged in three sections: correspondence, manuscripts, and restricted correspondence.
Selected Search Terms
Personal Names
Auden, W. H. (Wystan Hugh), 1907-1973.; Beckett, Samuel, 1906-1989.; Dunn, Douglas.; Golding, William, 1911-; Heaney, Seamus, 1939-; Hughes, Ted, 1930-1998.; Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972.; Muldoon, Paul.; Murphy, Richard, 1927-; Spender, Stephen, 1909-1995.
Corporate Names
Faber and Faber.
Topical Terms
Authors, English.; Authors and publishers--England.; Editors--England.; English literature--20th century.; English poetry--Irish authors--20th century.; Poets, Irish--20th century.; Literature publishing--England.; Publishers and publishing--England.
Occupation
Editor.
Container list
- Correspondence
- Auden, W.H. to CM, 8 June 1966, TLS, 1 p., re: the reissue of British Minor Poets of the Nineteenth Century, clerihews, and T.S. Eliot (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Beckett, Samuel to CM, 21 August 1987, ANS with envelope, re: thank you for letter (Box 1, Folder 2)
- [Bennett], Alan to CM, 8 March 1992, ACS, re: thank you for card (Box 1, Folder 3)
- [Bennett], Alan to CM, n.d., ACS, re: upcoming trip to New York, Muhamad Ali (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Dunn, Douglas to CM, 2 June 1982, TLS, 1 p., re: book launch of A Rumored City, upcoming move to Scotland and travels in Italy (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Dunn, Douglas to CM, 8 July 1986, TLS, 1 p.; with Arthur Callender to Dunn, Douglass, 23 June 1986, TLS [photocopy], 1 p.; with "To An Imposter," TMS, 1 p. and envelope, re: man posing as Douglas Dunn and possible legal action (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Golding, Bill [William] to CM, 11 December 1984, TLS, 1 p., re: new house and the possible derivation of the name "Tullimaar" (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Graham, Sydney [W.S.] to CM, 5 April 1976, ALS, 1 p., with dried leaves, re: progress on work (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Graham, Sydney [W.S.] and Nessie to CM, [ca. December 1981], ACS, re: New Year’s greetings (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Harris, Wilson to CM, 8 November 1993, ALS, 3 pp. with envelope and photograph, re: their first meeting, publication of Palace of the Peacock, and T.S. Eliot (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Heaney, Seamus [See Restricted correspondence] (Box -, Folder -)
- [Holloway], John to CM, 8 January [n.y.], ANS, re: gift book and hope to see CM (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Hughes, Ted to CM, 11 October 1987, ALS, 2 pp. with envelope, re: upcoming literary prize, the writing of Sorley MacLean and Michael Hoffman (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Hughes, Ted to CM, 18 August 1989, ALS, 2 pp., re: Derek Walcott and the Queen (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Hughes, Ted to CM, 30 September 1990, ALS, 2 pp. with envelope, re: 1991 Gold Medal, Sorley MacLean (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Hughes, Ted to CM, 8 July 1994, ACS, re: Golding exhibition, Craig Raine’s History: The Home Movie (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Lowell, Robert to CM, 25 June 1969, TLS, 1 p., re: inscription for Lowell’s Notebook (Box 1, Folder 10)
- McGahern, John to CM, 30 September 1993, ALS, 2 pp., re: plans to meet in London, work on a play (Box 1, Folder 11)
- McGahern, John to CM, n.d., ANS, re: CM’s trip to India (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Moore, Marianne to CM, 21 August 1948, ALS, 1 p., re: Thom Gunn, Stephen Spender, T.S. Eliot, and her regard for CM (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Moore, Marianne to CM, n.d., ALS, 1p., re: Thom Gunn (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Muldoon, Paul to CM, 27 July 1986, TLS, 1 p., re: CM's trip to Ireland, PM's move to Co. Kerry, and his writing (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Murdoch, Iris to CM, n.d., ANS, with envelope, re: thank you note for an enjoyable evening (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Murphy, Richard to CM, 6 October 1955, ALS, 4 pp. with envelope, re: planned move to Wicklow, Liam Miller, and The Archaeology of Love (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Murphy, Richard to CM, 6 June 1970, ALS, 2 pp., re: CM's recent visit, Robert Lowell, and weather (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Nicholson, Norman to CM, 6 Sep 1982, TLS, 1 p., re: death of Yvonne and satisfaction with his Selected Poems (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Ridler, Anne to CM, 30 January 1976, TLS, 1 p., re: chapbook by Vivian and upcoming radio broadcast of "The King of the Golden River" (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Rowse, A.L. to CM, 11 April 1987, ACS, re: reviews of his recent book and his contempt for "ordinary people" (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Rowse, A.L. to CM, n.d., ACS, re: name-dropping (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Spender, Stephen to CM, 1 March 1988, ALS, 1 p. with envelope, re: CM's letter regarding Spender's The Temple (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Wilson, Angus to CM, 4 November 1970, ALS, 1 p., re: Gwen Watkins' Dickens book (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Unidentified to CM, 23 October 1979, TLS, 1 p. with enclosure, re: enclosed limerick "A queen named old Mother Sims...", New York Public Library law suit over W.H. Auden's papers (see also manuscripts section) (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Unidentified to CM, n.d., ALS, 1 p. with envelope, re: recent poor health (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Manuscripts
- Auden, W.H., "Ode to the New Year (1939)," photocopied TS (2 copies) (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Auden, W.H., Untitled, limericks (2) "Said the Queen to the King..." and "There was an old maid..." MS, 1p. (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Auden, W.H., Untitled, limerick "A queen named old Mother Sims..." photocopied MS 1p. (see Correspondence, Unidentified to CM, 23 October 1979) (Box -, -)
- Restricted correspondence
- Heaney, Seamus to CM, 4 January 1982, TLS, 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Heaney, Seamus to CM, 21 June 1984, ALS, 2 pp. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Heaney, Seamus to CM, 26 October 1984, ALS, 1p. with envelope (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Heaney, Seamus to CM, 10 December 1985, ALS, 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Heaney, Seamus to CM, 5 April 1989, 2 pp. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Heaney, Seamus to CM, 19 July 1990, ACS (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Heaney, Seamus to CM, 3 March 1991, ALS, 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 1)